<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse concerning the holy fast of Lent together with the sentiment of Dr. John Cosens, late Bishop of Durrham, concerning the same holy fast.</title>
            <author>Francis, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1686</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A84862</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2060</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789323</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789323</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A84862)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2641:29)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse concerning the holy fast of Lent together with the sentiment of Dr. John Cosens, late Bishop of Durrham, concerning the same holy fast.</title>
                  <author>Francis, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, William Francis,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1686.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ Church (University of Oxford). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cosin, John, 1594-1672.</term>
               <term>Lent --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="discourse">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DISCOURSE Concerning the <hi>Holy Faſt of Lent:</hi> Together with the Sentiment of Dr. <hi>John Coſens,</hi> late Biſhop of <hi>Durrham,</hi> Concerning the ſame <hi>Holy Faſt.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Sacred Penitential Time of <hi>Lent</hi> is at hand, what ſhall I do? Shall I take notice of it, or no? If I do not take notice of it, ſome will ſtigmatize me as a <hi>Black Non-Conformiſt;</hi> and if I do take notice of it, others will calumniate me as a <hi>Papiſt</hi> in <hi>Maſquerade.</hi> O Times! O Manners! Unhappy Age in which we live! <hi>Diſſipavit Deus oſſa eorum qui hominibus placent: God has broken the Bones of thoſe who pleaſe Men.</hi> If I ſeek to pleaſe Men, or fear to offend them, I am no longer a Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, but a baſe Slave to the vile World. If I Chriſtianly obſerve this Sacred Time, my own Conſcience, I am ſure, will applaud me, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever my Neighbours may ſay or think of me: And a good Conſcience, even when it dictates Faſting and Abſtinence, is a continual Feaſt. But will not the Holy Goſpel ſay, I am Superſtitious? God forbid. I know they are the words of our Bleſſed Lord himſelf, <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.11. <hi>Not that which goes into the mouth, defiles a Man; but that which comes out of the mouth, this defiles a Man.</hi> And had he ſpoken theſe words, when it was objected to him by the Diſciples of St. <hi>John,</hi> that they and the Phariſees faſted often, but his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples faſted not the Objection would not ſo eaſily have been anſwered: But conſulting the Sacred Text, I find he is ſo far from diſparaging the Holy Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Faſting, by ſaying, <hi>Not that which goes into the mouth defiles,</hi> that he tacitly commends it, as a Duty too ſublime, for ſuch Novices in Religion as his Apoſtles as yet were, but the time would come when they ſhould faſt, to wit, after he ſhould be taken away from them, and ſhould have ſtrengthn'd them for ſo hard and neceſſary a Duty, by a plentiful effuſion of the Holy Ghoſt upon them. The new Wine of rigorous Abſtinence and Faſting was too ſtrong for the frail Bottles of our Lord's Diſciples, before their Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation from the Holy Ghoſt upon the day of <hi>Pentecoſt.</hi> But can then that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172632:2"/>which goes into my mouth defile me? Yes, when I eat or drink in contempt of the equitable and juſt command of my lawful Superiour, Eccleſiaſtical or Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil. Though ſtrictly ſpeaking, it is not the Meat then which defiles me, but my diſobedience to my Superiour.</p>
            <p>Not to engage in long diſputes: For theſe Reaſons methinks every good Chriſtian ought Religiouſly to obſerve <hi>The Holy Faſt of</hi> Lent.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe Faſting in it ſelf has ever been look'd upon by all Chriſtians as a Chriſtian Duty, and is not only highly commended by all the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the moſt Primitive times, but alſo by the Holy Scripture it ſelf; as having a ſingular Power to drive out the Devil: <hi>This Devil goes not out but by Prayer and Faſting:</hi> To obtain the Holy Ghoſt for our ſelves or others: (The Holy Apoſtles faſted and prayed, that the Holy Ghoſt might deſcend upon thoſe on whom they conferred Holy Orders.) To avert God's anger from a particular Perſon, City, or Country: Thus <hi>Ahab</hi> and the <hi>Ninivites</hi> appeaſed the wrath of the Almighty: To ſuppreſs Concupiſcence; to diſpoſe the Mind for Prayer; to encreaſe all Vertues in us in this Life, and our Crown of Glory in the other. If we faſt in a due manner, we have our Bleſſed Saviour's words for it, that we ſhall have a Reward in Heaven. If I faſt, to afflict and humble my ſelf before God Almighty for my Sins, my Faſting is an Act of Repentance. If I eat leſs my ſelf, that I may have more to give to thoſe that are in neceſſity, my Faſting is an act of Charity. If I faſt the better to diſpoſe my ſelf for Prayer, 'tis an Act of Religious Devotion. If I faſt, judging my ſelf not worthy of any Delicacies, nor of my fill even of the courſeſt Fare, 'tis an act of Humility, and diſpoſes my Soul moreover as little to affect fine Clothes or commodious Lodgings, as I do good Victuals, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently moderates my deſires of Money and Riches; which are not deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by corrupt Nature, but for theſe or ſuch like uſes. If I faſt, that I may be better able to pay my Debts, or provide my Children Portions, 'tis an act of Juſtice, and Chriſtian Paternal Piety. If to moderate my inordinate Appetite of Meat and Drink, 'tis an act of Temperance; and exceedingly diſpoſes to Temperance in the whole couſe of my life, when by experience I find my ſelf as chearful and contented, or rather more, upon a faſting day, than when I indulge to exceſs in eating and drinking. In fine, 'tis hard to name a Vertue which faſting does not ſtrangely help to procure, maintain, and increaſe. As for the four Cardinal Vertues, 'tis the formal exerciſe of the higheſt degree of Temperance; nor is Fortitude leſs ſeen in abſtaining from what pleaſes us, than in ſuſtaining what afflicts us. It makes Juſtice eaſie, and is the Mother of wiſe and ſober Thoughts. It moderates our Paſſions, defecates our Underſtandings, and makes us more fit for Contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of Natural or Supernatural Verities. <hi>O Angelical Abſtinencè!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Faſting</hi> then being of ſo ſingular uſe in a Chriſtian life, and Experience telling us, That thoſe who faſt only when they pleaſe, are pleaſed to faſt very ſeldom, or not at all; our Spiritual Prelates, who watch for our Souls good, can do no leſs than oblige us by a Law to faſt ſome times, nor ought we do no leſs than Religiouſly obſerve their equitable Commands.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I have all reaſon to think the Holy Faſt of Lent was firſt appointed by
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172632:2"/>the Holy Apoſtles themſelves, and conſequently ought to be Religiouſly ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeved by all good Chriſtians. For it cannot be imagined, that ſo many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Countries, Kings and Subjects, Prieſts and People, both of the Eaſtern and Weſtern Churches, could by chance fall upon the yearly practice of ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving ſo ſolemn a Faſt, and all at the ſame time before <hi>Eaſter:</hi> They muſt therefore either all at the firſt have been taught ſo by their firſt Maſters of Chriſtianity, which is the Concluſion intended to be proved; or ſome univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Supreme Authority, Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, muſt ſo have commanded them to do; or ſome Preachers firſt in one Country, &amp; then in an other, muſt ſo have perſuaded them to do in ſome Age ſince, that is, as a Pious thing, but not as inſtituted by the Apoſtles, and ſo received. But no Annals of our own, or other Chriſtian Countries, make any mention of any ſuch Preachers, or any ſuch Ordination made by any General Council, Pope, Prince, or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: Nor yet have we, or any other Chriſtian Countries, wanted Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical Hiſtorigraphers, who in their Memorials have taken notice of far leſſer matters than ſuch an Innovation as this muſt needs have been, had the Apoſtles taught the World no ſuch obſervance. And the truth is, 'tis pure Ignorance in Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory, and the Works of the Primitive Fathers, that makes ſo many waver in the Belief of the Apoſtolical Inſtitution of <hi>Lent;</hi> in which, if they were well converſant, they could not poſſibly doubt of it.</p>
            <p>Further: Not only two hundred years ago, but twelve hundred years ago, <hi>Lent</hi> was univerſally obſerved in the whole Chriſtian World, both in the Eaſtern and Weſtern Church, as is manifeſt out of the pious Works of the prime Pillars and Paſtors of Chriſt's Church, in the fourth and fifth Century of Chriſtianity. Nor do the oppoſers of <hi>Lent</hi> deny ſo much, and therefore appeal to the firſt 300 years after our Saviour; for which time, and which only, they pretend the Chriſtian Worſhip was untainted, and not infected with the ſuperſtitious Obſervation of <hi>Lent.</hi> Let us ſuppoſe then, that for the firſt 300 years of Chriſtianity, the Church of Chriſt in <hi>England, Italy, Greece,</hi> and other Countries, obſerved no ſuch thing as <hi>Lent-Faſt;</hi> and conſider by what means poſſible, the fourth Age could not only bring it in all over the Chriſtian World, but bring it in ſo ſecretly or covertly, that the prime Doctors of the fifth Age ſhould not be able to diſcern, that this new burden was ſuperadded to Chriſtianity by their immediate Progenitors, but ſhould be verily perſwaded, that ſuch an Obſervation had immemorially from Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to generation deſcended from the firſt planters of Chriſtianity, the Apoſtles: And yet it is evident, that the fifth Age did not only keep <hi>Lent,</hi> but alſo kept it as an Apoſtolical Inſtitution; and the prime Chriſtian Doctors of that Age have left it upon Record, in their deſervedly admired Works, that they kept this <hi>Holy Faſt</hi> as an obſervance taught them by Tradition from the Apoſtles. Hear their own words; <hi>S. Hierom,</hi> in his Epiſtle to <hi>Marcella: We faſt one Lent</hi> (Quadrageſimam) <hi>within the compaſs of a whole year, according to the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Apoſtles, in a ſeaſon fit for us. The Montaniſts keep three Lents in the year, as if three Saviours had ſuffered.</hi> Now if for the firſt 300 years there had been no ſuch obſervance by Chriſtians at <hi>Rome,</hi> but in the fourth Century ſome Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> or ſome Provincial or General Council, or Chriſtian
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:172632:3"/>Emperour, had firſt introduced it, could a Learned Prieſt of <hi>Rome</hi> of the fifth Age, who had lived and converſed with the prime Fathers of the fourth Age no leſs than 70 years, for he died <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 420. <hi>Aetatis Suae,</hi> 91. And one ſo well verſed in all Eccleſiaſtical matters, as <hi>S. Hierom</hi> was, err ſo groſly, as to miſtake ſo new an inſtitution for an Apoſtolical Tradition, that is, for an obſervance taught the City of <hi>Rome,</hi> from Father to Son, from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles? For the <hi>Greek</hi> Church, hear the Teſtimony of <hi>Theophilus,</hi> who was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary with <hi>St. Hierom</hi> and Patriarch of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> (to the Patriarchs of which See, it was entruſted by the firſt General Council, That they ſhould yearly ſignifie before-hand, to the reſt of the Churches, as well as their own, the true time of <hi>Eaſter.</hi>) In his firſt Paſchal Epiſtle, he writes thus: <hi>Let us cure the divers wounds of Vices,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And ſo may we enter the Faſts at hand, begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Lent the 30th day of the month</hi> Mechir, (as it were our <hi>February,</hi> the <hi>Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> reckoning 30 dayes in every Month.) <hi>The Week of the Salutary Paſch on the fifth day of the Month</hi> Pharmuth (or April,) <hi>and ending the Faſts according to the Evangelical Traditions on the evening of the</hi> Saturday, <hi>being the tenth of</hi> Phar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muth; <hi>and on the next Lords day, the</hi> 11th. <hi>of the ſame month, let us celebrate the Feaſts.</hi> I add the Teſtimony of S. <hi>Cyril.</hi> in his 20th. Homily The immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Succeſſor to the ſame <hi>Theophilus</hi> in the Patriarchſhip of <hi>Alexandria. De Feſtis Paſchalibus: So let us keep a pure faſt,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>beginning the Holy Lent from ſuch a day, ending alſo the Faſts on the</hi> 7th <hi>day of</hi> Pharmuth, <hi>late in the Evening, according to the Traditions Apoſtolical.</hi> The ſame S. <hi>Cyril,</hi> in nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen other of his Homilies, <hi>De Festis Paſchalibus,</hi> preached in ſo many ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years, refers the ſame Faſt of <hi>Lent</hi> to Tradition, Appointment, or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction Evangelical. <hi>The Law of abſtaining in Lent, was always in the Church,</hi> ſays the above-cited <hi>Theophilus Alexandrinus.</hi> Now can it be imagined, that theſe two Learned Patriarchs (to whom by the whole Chriſtian Church was committed the care of ſignifying the due time of <hi>Lent</hi> and <hi>Eaſter</hi>) had the Holy Faſt of <hi>Lent</hi> been ſo lately brought in by ſome Univerſal, Eccleſiaſtical or Civil Authority, could be ignorant of it, and tell all the World alſo, that they had been ſo taught to end <hi>Lent</hi> from Generation to Generation from the Apoſtles? Add hereunto the Diſcourſe of Learned Dr. <hi>Beverage</hi> againſt <hi>Dallee</hi> the <hi>French Huguenot,</hi> in his <hi>Codex Canonum Vindicatus.</hi> The Council of <hi>Nice</hi> the firſt General Chriſtian Council little more than 300 years after our B. Saviour, ordered that there ſhould be in all Chriſtian Provinces, two Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Councils every year; the one in <hi>Lent,</hi> the other in <hi>Autumn:</hi> whence that Learned Dr. inferrs that then <hi>Lent-Faſt</hi> was as well known all over the Chriſtian World as <hi>Autumn;</hi> and conſequently that <hi>Lent</hi> muſt of neceſſity have been appointed by the Apoſtles, otherwiſe ſuch an Univerſal Practice could not poſſibly have overſpread the Chriſtian World ſo early: Note alſo whereſoever <hi>Lent</hi> is obſerved, the Obſervers of it profeſs from Generation to Generation to have obſerved it, from the firſt planting of Chriſtianity amongſt them; nor does any of their Annals, Eccleſiaſtical or Civil, make any men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a later Inſtitution of it, and reflect, if the Holy Apoſtles had appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Lent</hi> by Oral Preaching, what other Arguments could we have had for its Apoſtolical Inſtitution?</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172632:3"/>
            <p>Hence it is, that the Holy Fathers of the Primitive Times, looked upon the obſervance of <hi>Lent,</hi> not as a matter only of Counſel, as left to our choice, whether we would obſerve it or no, but of Precept and O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bligation. Hear what St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſaies, <hi>Ser.</hi> 26. <hi>To faſt on other daies, may ſerve to promote either our Cure or our Reward; but not to faſt in</hi> Lent <hi>is a Sin. He that faſts at another time, ſhall receive his reward; but he who does not faſt in</hi> Lent <hi>ſhall be Puniſhed. Nor is it a light Sin to break the faſt of</hi> Lent, <hi>which was enjoyned by our Lord to the Faithful.— If thou wilt therefore be a Chriſtian, thou muſt do as Chriſt did.</hi> Thus That Great and Holy Prelate, who flouriſhed in the 4th. Age, and enlightned the whole Church of God with his Learning and Sanctity.</p>
            <p>But if the Apoſtles of our Lord <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> did recommend a year<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſervation of the Holy Faſt of <hi>Lent,</hi> to the ſeveral Countries by them Converted to the Chriſtian Faith, and ſuch an obſervation be of ſuch Singular benefit, and Spiritual advantage to all Chriſtians, how comes it to paſs that none of all their Writings which have come to our hands, makes expreſs mention of it? Hear Biſhop <hi>Gunning,</hi> p. 138. <hi>Ritual Obſervances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing viſible, and as it were legible in the univerſal Churches conſtant practice, needed not to be ſet down in her written Rule: Or thoſe which are therein ſet down, not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily ſo evidently, but that they might need the interpretation of ſuch the Churches practice.</hi> And indeed, whoever will impartially conſider the nature of the Books of the <hi>New Teſtament,</hi> will be ſo far from wondering, that all the Rituals of Chriſtianity are not expreſly declared in them, that he will rather wonder there is ſo much in them of the exterior Rites of Chriſtian Religion as there is. Had any of the Sacred Chriſtian Pen-men written a Book, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to declare the whole manner of Chriſtian Worſhip, like <hi>Moſes</hi> his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odus</hi> or <hi>Leviticus,</hi> we might reaſonably have expected an account, what days Chriſtians were to ſet a apart for Faſting or Religious Feaſting, what Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments they were to uſe for Divine Worſhip, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But they only, as is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Writing Books for other intents and purpoſes, by way of Hiſtory, for example, or moral Exhortations, and making mention only by the by of ſome of our Chriſtian Rites, as they occurr'd; nothing can be more unreaſonable then to expect in their ſaid Writings and expreſs clear mention of every Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Ceremonial Obſervance. And why <hi>St. Paul,</hi> or other of the Apoſtles, ſhould make mention of <hi>Lent</hi> in the Epiſtles they wrote to perſons already in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Chriſtian Faith, I underſtand not, unleſs perchance the perſons they wrote unto, had been deficient in obſerving it.</p>
            <p>But then again. What though the Holy Apoſtles did not firſt inſtitute the <hi>Lent Faſt,</hi> but it grew by little and little from the pious Obſervation of ſome particular Chriſtians into an univerſal Practice, ought not the Univerſal Practice of the whole Chriſtian Church, both <hi>Eastern</hi> and <hi>Western,</hi> of above 1200 years continuance, to have more poyſe with us, than the Non confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of a few New-faſhioned Chriſtians, ſprung up in the Night of this laſt Age? Beſides, we are commanded by our Civil and Eccleſiaſtical Superiours aſſembled in Parliament, to faſt <hi>Lent</hi> upon a Religious account, as appears by the Statute, 2 <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. of <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. c. 19. <hi>For as much as divers the Kings Subjects have of late time, more than in times paſt, broken and contemned ſuch Abſtinence,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172632:4"/>which has been uſed in this Realm upon the Friday and Saturday, the Emb'ring days, and other days, commonly called</hi> Vigils, <hi>and in the time commonly called</hi> Lent, <hi>and other accuſtomed Times, the King's Majeſty conſidering that due and godly Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinence, is a means to Vertue, and to ſubdue men's Bodies to their Soul and Spirit; and conſidering alſo that Fiſhers,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>doth Ordain and Enact, with the aſſent of the Lords Temporal and Spiritual,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That no perſon or perſons, of what Eſtate, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, or Condition he or they be, ſhall at any time after the Firſt day of</hi> May, 1549. <hi>willingly or unwillingly eat any manner of Fleſh upon any</hi> Friday <hi>or</hi> Saturday, <hi>or the</hi> Ember-daies, <hi>or on any day in the time commonly called</hi> Lent.</p>
            <p>Moreover if <hi>Lent</hi> be not to be obſerved upon a Religious account, In the name of God what does it in the Calender of the Liturgy or Book of <hi>Common-Prayer,</hi> more than Fairs and Markets? Reflect alſo with B. <hi>Gunning</hi> upon the Prayer for the firſt Sunday in <hi>Lent. O Lord, who for our ſakes did'st faſt forty days and forty nights, give us Grace to uſe ſuch Abstinence, that our Fleſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſubdued to the Spirit we may ever obey thy Godly motions in Righteouſneſs and true Holineſs,</hi> &amp;c. How unworthy it would be to make that Holy Prayer to bear ſuch a ſenſe as this; <hi>O Lord, who for our ſakes did'ſt faſt forty Days and forty Nights, give us Grace to uſe ſuch Abſtinence, that our Sea-faring Men, and Mariners, and young Cattel, and the like may be maintained.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To conclude, we offend the ſame all holy and all juſt God, by the ſame, if not worſe ſins than our fore-fathers Offended him, why ſhould we not ſeek to appeaſe his anger by the ſame Humiliations of Faſting and Abſtinence as they did? We have Bodies no leſs ſubject to concupiſcence than theirs, why not keep them in ſubjection by the ſame chaſtizements as they have done? We ſtand in need of the ſame Holy Ghoſt they did, why ſhould we expect to draw him down upon us but by Faſting and Prayer, as they did? Nor can our living in a Northernly Country excuſe us; our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors who lived under the ſame climate faſted often and rigorouſly. If we expect to go to the ſame Heaven with them, we muſt expect to go by the ſame rough path of Chriſtian Temperance as they went. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the abounding of all iniquity amongſt us, Covetouſneſs, Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Glutony, Laſciviouſneſs, Pride, Malice, Shedding of Innocent, blood, Profaneſs, Perjury, Blaſphemy, Infidelity, Atheiſm, cry aloud to Gods Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance againſt us, and call every devout Chriſtian to Faſting, Weeping and Mourning to prevent thoſe temporal Judgments we may juſtly fear, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thoſe ſpiritual plagues of Diviſions, Ignorance and Error, which we too ſenſibly feel, <hi>In that day,</hi> ſaies the Holy Prophet, <hi>Eſay.</hi> Chap. 22. V. 12, 13, 14. <hi>Did the Lord God of Hoſts call to Weeping, and to Mourning, and to Baldneſs, and to girding with Sackcloath; and behold joy and gladneſs, ſlaying Oxen and killing Sheep, eating Fleſh and drinking Wine: let us eat and drink for to morrow we ſhall die. And it was revealed in mine ears by the Lord of Hoſts, ſurely this iniquity ſhall not be purged from you till you die, ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts.</hi> Reflect here how the Holy Prophet, by Gods own Command declares, The eating of Fleſh and drinking Wine, when God calls to faſting, weeping, and mourning, to be an iniquity, which ſhall ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be forgiven. And when does Almighty God call to faſting, weeping, and mourning, if he do not call then, when our own and others ſins re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172632:4"/>it, and when the practice of the whole Chriſtian World in all Ages invites to it, and when our lawful Superiors, who watch for our Souls good, poſitively command it?</p>
            <p>Whom all that has been ſaid cannot perſwade to a Religious obſervation of the Penitential time of <hi>Lent,</hi> I have yet this one reaſonable requeſt to make them, that they would but for one year, faſt as many days out of Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Devotion, as they do who faſt at ſet-times and days, commanded by an extrinſecal Authority; and I perſwade my ſelf, they would find ſo great ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual benefit thereby, that they would clearly ſee, faſting being good in it ſelf, its being commanded by our Superiors can never make it Superſtition. I deny not, but the change of the Primitive Chriſtian way of faſting into a meer abſtinence from Fleſh, by Set-Faſters, faſting from one ſort of meat and feaſting upon others, making up what they wanted in Meat, by Wine and ſtrong Drink, at meals and betwixt meals, gave but two great occaſion to many ſimple well meaning people, to look upon all faſting as a meer ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition. But a practiſe good and holy in it ſelf, as this has been ſhew'd to be, ought not to be caſt away for ſome abuſes, committed by diſordered li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in the obſervance of it: none will do this, but ſuch as are led by the Spirit of Contention. If we will needs contend, let it be who ſhall ſpend moſt of our time in devout prayers, and diligent reading, or hearing Gods word; and moſt of our worldly wealth in charitable Alms upon our indigent neighbour, and leaſt upon our ſelves in meat and drink: Let none revile or injure his brother, but let our great quarrel be againſt our ſelves, Judging and Puniſhing our ſelves for our ſins, by Faſting and Abſtinence in this world, that we may not be Judged and Puniſhed for them by Almighty God by Hell-fire in the other. By ſuch Contentions and Emulations as theſe, we ſhall ſooner come to an amicable union amongſt our ſelves, and to the happy favour of our common Lord and God, than by all our uncharita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble unchriſtian Brawls and Conteſts.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Sentiment of Dr. <hi>John Coſens,</hi> late B. of <hi>Durham,</hi> concerning the <hi>H. Faſt</hi> of <hi>Lent.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BY the Antient Laws, and Cuſtom of the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> We ſtill Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve a Yearly, and a more ſolemn Time of Faſting and Prayer, than ordinary; which, from the Seaſon wherein it falls, we call our<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Or,</hi> Spring-Faſt; for <hi>Lent</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies the <hi>Spring</hi> in the <hi>Saxon</hi> Language.</note> 
                  <hi>Lent <hi>Faſt:</hi>
                  </hi> A Time, wherein the <hi>Church</hi> Commemorates the Miraculous <hi>Faſting</hi> of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and by it commendeth the like Ghoſtly and Religious Exerciſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, as being the readieſt Means we can uſe againſt the Temptations of the Devil, and the ſinful Deſires of our pamper'd Fleſh. Not, as if She thought we were able to Faſt as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did, and Live altogether without Meat and Drink: Or, as if Her meaning were, to Tye us unto any ſuch ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous Abſtinence, which refuſeth ſome kinds of Meats, as being unclean in themſelves; but, as far as our Imperfections and Infirmities would ſuffer us, we ſhould Tye our ſelves to ſuch a Religious <hi>Faſt</hi> and <hi>Abſtinence,</hi> as thereby, either interrupting, or otherwiſe abating, not only the kind, but, the quantity of our Diet; and ſo taking the leſs care of our bodily Suſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172632:5"/>we might the more earneſtly hunger and thirſt after Righteouſneſs, which is the Food of our Souls; and by mortifying our ſinful Fleſh, fix our Minds on heavenlier and better Deſires. A <hi>Lent</hi> ſo kept, will Conform us the better to our <hi>Saviour</hi>'s Sufferings, which are now remembred; and make us the more capable, and more ſenſible of the Joy which the Church<note n="†" place="margin">Both by the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt,</hi> and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther holy Offices.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſeth, in the Joyful Solemnity of <hi>Eaſter,</hi> as well in Commemoration of <hi>His,</hi> as in hope of Our glorious and gladſom <hi>Reſurrection.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And after this manner, hath it been religiouſly obſerved throughout all Ages, both in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Church.</p>
               <p>For the <hi>Greeks</hi> firſt, It is mentioned by <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who was St. <hi>John</hi>'s Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Philippians,</hi> a Writing unqueſtioned by moſt Men: Then by <hi>Irenaeus,</hi> who was St. <hi>John</hi>'s Schollar alſo, but once removed: by <hi>Origen,</hi> who lived not long after them, in the <hi>tenth Homily</hi> upon <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus:</hi> by the famous General Council of<note n="*" place="margin">Can. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>Nice,</hi> not much above <hi>three Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> Years after <hi>Chriſt,</hi> where they mention the <note n="†" place="margin">Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma.</note> 
                  <hi>Forty dayes of Lent,</hi> as a known thing Inſtituted and Obſerved by all Men, long before their time: After them, by St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> in his <hi>Catechiſm:</hi> and by St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> in his Sermons upon <hi>Geneſis,</hi> which were preach'd in this time of <hi>Lent:</hi> by St. <hi>Baſil,</hi> in his <hi>ſecond Homily</hi> of <hi>Faſting,</hi> where he tells us, <hi>That there was no age,</hi> nor no place, but both knew it, and obſerved it: by <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in his Relation <hi>ad Orthodox:</hi> by St. <hi>Gregory Nyſſen,</hi> in his Sermon of <hi>Baptiſm:</hi> and by <hi>Nazianzen,</hi> Surnamed the <hi>Divine,</hi> in his Sermon of <hi>Almes-Deeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then for the <hi>Latins,</hi> By <hi>Tertullion</hi> firſt, who was the firſt of the <hi>Latin Fathers,</hi> and ſpake more concerning the <hi>Lent-Faſt,</hi> than perhaps the <hi>Church</hi> would have had him: by St. <hi>Cyprian</hi> after him, who was alſo his Scholar: By St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Hierom,</hi> and St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> in more than Forty ſeveral places of their Writings: After them, by a whole Cloud of <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> even to our own Times. All which, being put together, will prove abundantly, that the <hi>Lent</hi> which we now keep, is, and ever has been, an <hi>Apoſtolical Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution:</hi> As St. <hi>Hierom</hi> ſaid in his <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to <hi>Marcella; Nos <hi>unam Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drageſimam,</hi> ſecundum Traditionem <hi>Apoſtolorum,</hi> tempore nobis Congruo jejuna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus:</hi> That is, <hi>We obſerve a <hi>Lent-Faſt</hi> of <hi>Forty Dayes,</hi> as we have been taught by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> in a fit and ſeaſonable time of the year.</hi> We add out of St. <hi>Auguſtin,</hi> in his 119 <hi>Epistle</hi> to <hi>Ianuaríus,</hi> a known place; <hi>Quadrageſima Jejuniorum habet authoritatem,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The <hi>Lenten-Faſt</hi>
                  </hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is authorized, both by the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New-Teſtament;</hi> there by <hi>Moſes,</hi> and here by <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </hi> And out of <hi>Chryſologus,</hi> in his <hi>eleventh</hi> Sermon, <hi>Quod <hi>Quadrageſimam</hi> j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>junamus, non est humana Inventio,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>It is no <hi>Human Invention</hi>
                  </hi> (as they call it) <hi>but it comes from Divine <hi>Authority,</hi> that we Faſt our <hi>Forty-dayes</hi> in <hi>Lent.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod univerſa tenet Eccleſia, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c Conciliis conſtitutum, ſed ſemper retentum eſt; non niſi Apoſtolica autoritate traditum rectiſſime creditur. St.</hi> Auguſt. de Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſmo contra Donatiſtas. <hi>That which the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church obſerveth, and was not inſtituted by Councils, but has been ever retained; we moſt rightly believe to have been no other, than a Tradition from Apoſtolical Authority.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Printed for the Author, <hi>William Francis.</hi> 1686.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:172632:5"/>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:172632:6"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:172632:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172632:7"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
